Guide to the Havelock Ellis Correspondence
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Havelock Ellis Correspondence
1894-1950.
Ellis, Havelock, 1859-1939.
1 box (111 items)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0386
4078732
Biographical Note
Havelock Ellis was a British psychologist, sexologist, and physician. His 1987 book Sexual Inversion is one of the major early works on homosexuality.
Scope and Content
Letters written to Havelock Ellis, including several drafts of his replies, and a few letters to his executrix, Mrs. Françoise Lafitte-Cyon. Nearly all of the letters relate to to Ellis' writings and their influence, as well as the work of his correspondents in the fields of sex studies, pornography, birth control, and pacifism. Correspondents include Henri Barbusse, André Breton, Elie Faure, Robert J. Gibbings, Julian Huxley, Desmond MacCarthy, Bronislaw Malinowski, Naomi Mitchison, John Middleton Murray, Henry S. Salt, and Marie Stopes.
Subjects
Lafitte-Cyon, Françoise.; Barbusse, Henri, 1873-1935.; Breton, André, 1896-1966.; Faure, Elie, 1873-1937.; Gibbings, Robert J.; Huxley, Julian, 1887-1975.; MacCarthy, Desmond, 1877-1952.; Malinowski, Bronislaw, 1884-1942.; Mitchison, Naomi, 1897-1999.; Murry, John Middleton, 1889-1957.; Salt, Henry Stephens, 1851-1939.; Stopes, Marie Carmichael, 1880-1958.; Sex.; Pornography.; Birth control.; Pacifism.; English literature--19th century.; English literature--20th century.; Authors, English.
Acquisition
1976 M-76 09484F Purchase
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Allen of Hurtwood, Reginald Clifford (Box 1)
  - Atkinson, Edward Tindal, 1878-1957 (Box 1)
  - Barbusse, Henri, 1873-19 35 (Box 1)
  - Bedford, William Sackville Russell Hastings, 12th Duke of, 1888-1954 (Box 1)
  - Blacker, Carlos Paton, 1895- (Box 1)
  - Breton, André, 1896-1966 (Box 1)
  - Buckton, Alice Mary (Box 1)
  - Burns, John Eliot, 1858-1943 (Box 1)
  - Burrow, Trigant, 18 75-1950 (Box 1)
  - Collis, John Stewart, 1900- (Box 1)
  - Constantine, Murray, pseud. (Box 1)
  - Dodgson, Edward Spencer, 1357- (Box 1)
  - Ellis, Henry Havelock, 1859-1939 (Box 1)
  - Ellis, Stewart Marsh (Box 1)
  - Faure, Elie, 1873-1937 (Box 1)
  - Féré, Charles Samson, 1852-1907 (Box 1)
  - Ferrars, Max Henry (Box 1)
  - Flexner, Abraham, 1863-1959 (Box 1)
  - Freeman, Richard Austin, 1862-1943 (Box 1)
  - Gibbings, Robert John, 1839-1953 (Box 1)
  - Goldberg, Isaac, 1887-1938 (Box 1)
  - Gutierrez-Gili, Juan (Box 1)
  - Haire, Norman, 1892-1953 (Box 1)
  - Hirschfeld, Magnus, 1868-1935 (Box 1)
  - Hobson, John Atkinson, 1858-1940 (Box 1)
  - Hoppé E.O., 1878-1971 (Box 1)
  - Horder, Thomas Jeeves, 1st Bt., 1871-1955 (Box 1)
  - Huxley, Julian Sorell, 1887-1975 (Box 1)
  - Keyserling, Hermann, 1880-1946 (Box 1)
  - Leach, Bernard Lowell, 1887- (Box 1)
  - MacCarthy, Desmond, 1877-1952 (Box 1)
  - Malinowski, Bronislaw Kaspar, 1884-1942 (Box 1)
  - Malleson, William Miles, 1833- (Box 1)
  - Mannin, Ethel, 1900- (Box 1)
  - Meyer, Adolf, 1866-1950 (Box 1)
  - Mitchison, Naomi (Haldane), 1897- (Box 1)
  - Moore, Thomas Sturge, 1870-1944 (Box 1)
  - Munsterberg, Hugo, 1365-1916 (Box 1)
  - Murry, John Middleton, 1389-1957 (Box 1)
  - Orage, Alfred, 1875-1934 (Box 1)
  - Peterson, Houston, 1397- (Box 1)
  - Platt, William (Box 1)
  - Richthofen, Baron Oswald von, 1847-1906 (Box 1)
  - Riviere, Isabelle (Mrs. Jacques) (Box 1)
  - Rolleston, Humphrey Davy, 1862-1944 (Box 1)
  - St. Denis, Ruth, 1880-1968 (Box 1)
  - Salt, Henry Stephens, 1851-1939 (Box 1)
  - Saurat, Denis, 1890-1958 (Box 1)
  - Stopes, Marie Carmichael, 1880-1958 (Box 1)
  - Watson, Elliot Lovegood Grant, 1385-1970 (Box 1)
  - Westermarck, Edward Alexander, 1832-1939 (Box 1)
  - Wood, James (Box 1)